<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix [
<!ENTITY % isopub PUBLIC "ISO 8879:1986//ENTITIES Publishing//EN//XML" "http://www.w3.org/2003/entities/iso8879/isopub.ent">
<!ENTITY % isonum PUBLIC "ISO 8879:1986//ENTITIES Numeric and Special Graphic//EN" "http://www.w3.org/2003/entities/iso8879/isonum.ent">
<!ENTITY % isotech PUBLIC "ISO 8879:1986//ENTITIES General Technical//EN" "http://www.w3.org/2003/entities/iso8879/isotech.ent">
%isopub;%isonum;%isotech;
<!ENTITY % myEnt SYSTEM "teco.ent">
%myEnt;
]>
 <appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1" xml:id="APP_RSTS"><title>RSTS/E Operating Characeristics</title>
 <sect1 xml:id="APP_RSTS_STA"><title>Startup</title>
 <para>
 RSTS supports all of the standard TECO invocation commands,
 namely:
 <informaltable>
 <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="c1"/>
<colspec colname="c2"/>

 <tbody>
<row><entry><para/></entry><entry><para>TECO</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para/></entry><entry><para>TECO filespec</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para/></entry><entry><para>TECO filespec=filespec</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para/></entry><entry><para>MAKE filespec</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para/></entry><entry><para>MUNG filespec</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para/></entry><entry><para>MUNG filespec,text</para></entry></row>
 
</tbody>
</tgroup></informaltable>
 </para><para>
 The CCL command switches /DETACH and /SIZE:n (or /SIZE:+n) can be
 used with TECO. If /DETACH is used and the user's detached-job
 quota has not yet been reached, TECO will detach the job before
 any further processing. If /SIZE:n is used, TECO will pre-expand
 the text and Q-register storage area to nK. If /SIZE:+n is used,
 TECO will set the text storage and Q-register storage area to
 n+4K initially (TECO's default startup size is 4K).
 </para></sect1><sect1 xml:id="APP_RSTS_FS"><title>File Specification</title>
 <para>
 The file access commands ER, EB, EW, and EI accept a file
 specification in the standard RSTS/E format:
 <informaltable>
 <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="c1"/>
<colspec colname="c2"/>

 <tbody>
<row><entry><para/></entry><entry><para>dev:[p,pn]filename.ext</para></entry></row>
 
</tbody>
</tgroup></informaltable>
 </para><para>
 in which dev: is a physical device name or a logical device
 name; if dev: is not specified, the public structure is
 assumed. If [p,pn] is not specified, the user's current logged
 in account is assumed. The filename field must be specified
 whenever the device name references a file structured device.
 The .ext field is a file extension and must be explicitly given
 if used. There is no default extension except for EI commands
 which default the .ext field to .TEC.
 </para><para>
 The file specification switches /n, /B+, /, and /B2 may be
 applied to the ER, EW, and EB commands. These switches invoke
 special handling of program lines containing <!-- <LF> --> or &amp;
 continuation characters. See <xref linkend="APP_BPX"/> for more information.
 </para><para>
 The file specification switch /B causes TECO to handle the file
 as a stream of 8-bit binary characters; normal ASCII format
 processing (such as removal of null characters) is not done.
 </para><para>
 The file specification switches /RONLY, /MODE:n, and
 /CLUSTERSIZE:n can be included in a file specification. TECO
 automatically opens any disk input file in /RONLY mode. The file
 size switches /FILESIZE:n and /SIZE:n might leave an output file
 larger than the amount of data output by TECO. These file size
 switches are therefore illegal and produce an error if included
 in a file specification.
 </para><para>
 The EB and EW commands also accept the extended notation for an
 output file protection code
 <informaltable>
 <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="c1"/>
<colspec colname="c2"/>

 <tbody>
<row><entry><para/></entry><entry><para>dev:[p,pn]filename.ext<literal>&lt;prot></literal></para></entry></row>
 
</tbody>
</tgroup></informaltable>
 </para><para>
 The optional <literal>&lt;prot></literal> specifies the output file protection code.
 </para></sect1><sect1 xml:id="APP_RSTS_BF"><title>Backup Files</title>
 <para>
 The EB command maintains one level of file backup on RSTS/E. The
 pre-edited input file name is changed to
 <informaltable>
 <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="c1"/>
<colspec colname="c2"/>

 <tbody>
<row><entry><para/></entry><entry><para>filename.BAK</para></entry></row>
 
</tbody>
</tgroup></informaltable>
 </para><para>
 before the new output file is closed with the original name.
 Only normal file closing commands (EC, EF, EG, and EX) cause this
 renaming to happen. If TECO is aborted or the output file is
 purged by the EK command, the input filename remains unchanged.
 Note only one .BAK file for a given name is kept; earlier .BAK
 backup files are deleted each time a new backup file is created.
 </para><para>
 A good policy to follow when editing is to close the edited file
 frequently enough so that an unexpected incident would not cause
 a substantial loss of work. Files should be backed up regularly.
 TECO has the power to let an unsuspecting user alter a good file
 into a completely useless state. The FILCOM program can be used
 to verify an editing session.
 </para></sect1><sect1 xml:id="APP_RSTS_EG"><title>EXIT and GO</title>
 <para>
 If TECO is exited via the EGstring<!-- <accent>(grave) --> command, the "string" is
 executed as a RSTS/E CCL command after the input and output
 file(s) are closed.
 </para></sect1><sect1><title>ET Flag Handling</title>
 <para>
 Bit 6 (detach) is handled specially by TECO. Every time the ET
 flag is read (used as a numeric value), TECO ensures that Bit 6
 is on if the job is attached or off if the job is detached. This
 allows a TECO macro to check for "detachedness". If an attempt
 is made to set Bit 6 and the user's detached-job quota has been
 reached, the request is ignored and Bit 6 will read back as a 0
 (assuming the job is attached). If Bit 6 is set and the user's
 detached-job quota has not yet been reached, the job will become
 detached. Further reading of Bit 6 will return a 1, indicating
 the detached condition.
 </para></sect1></appendix>
