<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix [
<!ENTITY % isopub PUBLIC "ISO 8879:1986//ENTITIES Publishing//EN//XML" "http://www.w3.org/2003/entities/iso8879/isopub.ent">
<!ENTITY % isonum PUBLIC "ISO 8879:1986//ENTITIES Numeric and Special Graphic//EN" "http://www.w3.org/2003/entities/iso8879/isonum.ent">
<!ENTITY % isotech PUBLIC "ISO 8879:1986//ENTITIES General Technical//EN" "http://www.w3.org/2003/entities/iso8879/isotech.ent">
%isopub;%isonum;%isotech;
<!ENTITY % myEnt SYSTEM "teco.ent">
%myEnt;
]>
 <appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1" xml:id="APP_VTE"><title>VTEDIT &ndash; A keypad editing macro for TECO-11 and TECO-32</title>
 <section xml:id="APP_VTE_INTRO"><title>Introduction</title>
 <para>
 The Video Terminal Editor (called VTEDIT) is a feature of the
 TECO text editor which is available under RSTS/E, RT-11, RSX-11M,
 IAS, and VAX/VMS. VTEDIT allows you to see all changes to the
 text as you make them.
 </para><para>
 The Video Terminal Editor has two parts:
 <itemizedlist>
 <listitem><para>The scope driver, which keeps the terminal screen updated,
 is a part of the TECO run-time system (RSTS/E), the TECO.SAV
 program (RT-11), the TEC.TSK task (RSX-11M and IAS), or the
 TEC.EXE image (VAX/VMS).
 </para></listitem><listitem><para>The keyboard interface, which accepts your typed input and
 either inserts it into the text buffer or interprets it as
 an editing command, is a TECO macro called VTEDIT.TEC.
 </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
 </para><para>
 This appendix describes the scope driver and the VTEDIT macro.
 The scope driver is a standard part of TECO. However, VTEDIT is
 just one of many possible keyboard interfaces. Your installation
 may have modified it, and therefore may have its own version of
 the scope editing keyboard interface.
 </para><para>
 </para><section><title>How to read this appendix</title>
 <para>
 The following conventions are used throughout this appendix:
 <itemizedlist>
 <listitem><para>An underlined dollar sign (<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>) indicates typing the ESCape
 key.
 </para></listitem><listitem><para>The notation 'CTRL/x' indicates a control character, which
 you enter by holding down the CTRL key and typing the
 indicated character.
 </para></listitem><listitem><para>Items in square brackets are optional.
 </para></listitem><listitem><para>The letter 'n' indicates a numeric argument. You enter a
 numeric argument by typing <emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>[&ndash;] followed by a series of
 digits. The short sequence <emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>&ndash; is equivalent to <emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>&ndash;1.
 The first non-numeric keystroke you type after entering a
 numeric argument should be an editing function which takes
 an argument. Any other keystroke will cause the editor to
 discard the number. (It is also possible for a numeric
 argument to be an expression using standard operators. This
 is discussed later in the appendix.) Unless otherwise stated,
 the editor uses a default value of 1 if you omit an optional
 argument.
 </para></listitem><listitem><para>The letter 'q' indicates any alphabetic Q-register name. If
 the syntax of the editor requires a Q-register name and you
 type any non-alphabetic character, VTEDIT sounds the
 terminal bell and ignores the command.
 </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
 </para></section><section><title>Invoking the Video Terminal Editor Macro</title>
 <para>
 The Video Terminal Editor macro is stored in the file VTEDIT.TEC.
 For RSTS/E and VAX/VMS, the file is usually stored in the system
 library (SY:$ for RSTS/E, SYS$LIBRARY: for VAX/VMS). Other
 operating systems may store VTEDIT.TEC elsewhere; this appendix
 uses VAX/VMS for its examples. When you use the macro, it resides
 in Q-register I and uses all of the numeric Q-registers. (The
 macro saves these Q-registers when it starts and restores them
 when it exits, but they are unavailable from command mode while
 the macro is executing.) To load Q-register I with VTEDIT,
 execute the following TECO command:
 <informaltable>
 <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="c1"/>
<colspec colname="c2"/>

 <tbody>
<row><entry><para/></entry><entry><para>EI$VTEDIT<emphasis role="underline">$$</emphasis></para></entry></row>
 
</tbody>
</tgroup></informaltable>
 </para><para>
 The message 'VTEDIT.TEC loaded into Q-Reg I' is printed to
 confirm the load. Start the macro by typing the TECO command:
 <informaltable>
 <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="c1"/>
<colspec colname="c2"/>

 <tbody>
<row><entry><para/></entry><entry><para>MI<emphasis role="underline">$$</emphasis></para></entry></row>
 
</tbody>
</tgroup></informaltable>
 </para><para>
 These two commands cannot be in the same command sequence. You
 must execute the EI command before you can execute Q-register I.
 </para><para>
 If you use the DCL commands TECO or MAKE to invoke TECO, you can
 automatically load and start the VTEDIT macro by including the
 following switch after the DCL command name:
 <informaltable>
 <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="c1"/>
<colspec colname="c2"/>

 <tbody>
<row><entry><para/></entry><entry><para>/VT</para></entry></row>
 
</tbody>
</tgroup></informaltable>
 </para><para>
 If you always want VTEDIT included, create a TECO start-up
 command file called TECO.INI in your account. This file can
 contain any TECO commands, and should end with the following
 commands:
 <informaltable>
 <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="c1"/>
<colspec colname="c2"/>

 <tbody>
<row><entry><para/></entry><entry><para>ET&amp;512"N 1+ ' 0</para></entry></row>
 
</tbody>
</tgroup></informaltable>
 </para><para>
 Then, whenever you use the TECO or MAKE DCL commands on a DEC_CRT
 terminal, TECO automatically loads and starts VTEDIT. To
 suppress this loading, you must start editing with the command:
 <informaltable>
 <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="c1"/>
<colspec colname="c2"/>

 <tbody>
<row><entry><para/></entry><entry><para>TECO/NOINIT</para></entry></row>
 
</tbody>
</tgroup></informaltable>
 </para><para>
 The model TECO.INI file 
 does a more advanced set of checks as well as implementing some
 other random things (such as humorous messages based on the time
 of day). Of course, experimentation is encouraged.
 </para></section><section><title>Interpreting the Terminal Screen</title>
 <para>
 While you are running the Video Terminal Editor macro, your
 terminal screen displays up to 24 lines of the text in TECO's
 text buffer. This 'window' into your buffer always includes the
 current line (the line containing the text pointer). The
 location of the text pointer within the buffer is indicated by
 the terminal's cursor. All characters that you type on the
 keyboard that are not commands to VTEDIT are immediately inserted
 into the text buffer at the current pointer position and are
 displayed on the screen.
 </para><para>
 Certain other special symbols can appear on the screen:
 <itemizedlist>
 <listitem><para>A '<!-- <graphic>(F\F) -->' symbol indicates the
 end of your text buffer and signifies that there is an
 implicit form feed at the end of the buffer.
 </para></listitem><listitem><para>A diamond (&diams;) indicates the
 end of your text buffer if there is no implicit form feed
 there.
 </para></listitem><listitem><para>A diamond (&diams;) immediately
 following one of the buffer end symbols above signifies that
 your input file is at end-of-file.
 </para></listitem><listitem><para>A '<!-- <graphic>(L\F) -->' symbol indicates that
 the text pointer is positioned between a carriage return and
 a line feed. This symbol appears only as the first symbol
 on a line, and it overlays the first character of the line.
 It allows you to tell the difference between the text
 pointer being at the start of a line of text and being just
 before the end of it.
 </para></listitem><listitem><para>A '<!-- <graphic>(N\L) -->' symbol indicates that
 the current line of text is too long to fit on the current
 line of the screen. If TECO's truncate flag bit (bit 8,
 value 256) is not set in the ET flag word (the normal case),
 the remainder of the text appears on the next line of the
 screen, preceded by the '<!-- <graphic>(N\L) -->' 
 and a space. If the truncate flag is set (via the TECO
 command ET#256ET), the remainder of the text is not
 displayed, but the special symbol appears at the end of the
 line to remind you that there are characters which cannot be
 displayed. You can control the number of characters that
 appear on each line by using the CTRL/V command.
 </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
 </para><para>
 If you are using a DEC_CRT terminal in ANSI mode, VTEDIT will
 display any text between the current text pointer and the marked
 buffer location (see the Set Mark command) in reverse video to
 highlight the marked region.
 </para><para>
 A feature of the scope driver which allows you to view the exact
 contents of your text buffer is called 'see-all' mode. When
 see-all mode is turned on, all special characters and hidden
 spacing are visible on the screen as special graphic symbols:
 <informaltable>
 <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="c1"/>
<colspec colname="c2"/>

 <tbody>
<row><entry><para>TAB</para></entry><entry><para> appears as a or '<!-- <graphic>(H\T) -->' symbol. The spacing after the tab, which is
          normally blank space on the screen that does not correspond to any characters in the text,
          is shown as a series of centered dots (·).</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para>LINE FEED</para></entry><entry><para>
 not immediately preceeded by a RETURN appears as a
 '<!-- <graphic>(L\F) -->' symbol. If the
 line feed is in the middle of the line, the blank
 space at the beginning of the next line is filled
 (as for TAB).
 </para><para>
 A LINE FEED immediately after a RETURN is not
 displayed with any special symbol (see RETURN
 below).</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para>RETURN</para></entry><entry><para>
 followed by a line feed appears as a '<!-- <graphic>(C\R) -->' symbol. Any blank space
 before the end of the line is thus visible.
 </para><para>
 A RETURN causing an overprint line (i.e., a RETURN
 not immediately followed by a LINE FEED) appears
 as a not-equal (&ne;) sign. The
 overprint characters are displayed on the next
 line instead of over (and thus clobbering) the
 original characters. This allows full viewing of
 all characters in overprint lines.</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para>FORM FEED</para></entry><entry><para>
 appears as a '<!-- <graphic>(F\F) -->' symbol.
 No extra blank lines are shown. If the
 form feed is in the middle of the line, the blank
 space at the beginning of the next line is filled.</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para>VERTICAL TAB</para></entry><entry><para>
 appears as a '<!-- <graphic>(V\T) -->' symbol. If the vertical tab is in the
 middle of the line, the blank space at the
 beginning of the next line is filled.</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para>ESCAPE</para></entry><entry><para>
 appears as a Greek pi (&#x3c0;)
 to distinguish it from a dollar sign.</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para>CTRL/x</para></entry><entry><para>
  appears as a plus-or-minus (&plusmn;) sign 
 followed by the character 'x' to distinguish it
 from a real uparrow.</para></entry></row>
 
</tbody>
</tgroup></informaltable>
 </para></section><section><title>Numeric Arguments</title>
 <para>
 Simple numeric arguments consist of ESCape, an optional minus
 sign, and a digit string which is always interpreted in decimal.
 None of the keystrokes of a simple numeric argument echo on the
 terminal.
 </para><para>
 More advanced numeric arguments can be expressions using standard
 arithmetic operators. These numeric arguments also start with
 ESCape, an optional minus sign, and, then, a digit. If the first
 non-digit typed is one of the valid operators listed below,
 expression mode is entered. The top line of the display is
 erased and a line of the form:
 <informaltable>
 <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="c1"/>
<colspec colname="c2"/>

 <tbody>
<row><entry><para/></entry><entry><para>Radix x, Expression arg1 op arg2</para></entry></row>
 
</tbody>
</tgroup></informaltable>
 </para><para>
 is displayed. The initial radix is 10, arg1 will be the initial
 digit string, and op will be the operator.
 </para><para>
 Further digit string typing will fill in arg2 until a non-digit
 is typed. If it is another valid operator, the current
 arg1 op arg2 expression will be evaluated, the result will
 replace arg1, arg2 will be set to zero, and op will be the typed
 operator.
 </para><para>
 If it is a radix change command, the radix is immediately
 changed. No evaluation of the expression occurs. The radix
 change is local to the current numeric expression; it is not
 subsequently remembered.
 </para><para>
 If it is an arg2 stand-in, the current arg2 is replaced by the
 specified value.
 </para><para>
 If it is RUBOUT, the current arg2 is reset to zero.
 </para><para>
 If it is CTRL/U, the entire expression is abandoned and the
 display is fixed up.
 </para><para>
 Else it is assumed to be an editing command. The current
 arg1 op arg2 will be evaluated and the result becomes the numeric
 argument to that command.
 </para><para>
 The valid numeric expression operators are:
 <informaltable>
 <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="c1"/>
<colspec colname="c2"/>

 <thead>
<row>
<entry><para>Operator</para></entry><entry><para>Operation</para></entry>
</row>
</thead>
 <tbody>
<row><entry><para>+</para></entry><entry><para>Addition</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para>&ndash;</para></entry><entry><para>Subtraction</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para>*</para></entry><entry><para>Multiplication</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para>/</para></entry><entry><para>Division</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para>#</para></entry><entry><para>Logical .OR.</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para>&amp;</para></entry><entry><para>Logical .AND.</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para>=</para></entry><entry><para>Evaluate current arg1 op arg2</para></entry></row>
 
</tbody>
</tgroup></informaltable>
 </para><para>
 The valid radix change commands are:
 <informaltable>
 <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="c1"/>
<colspec colname="c2"/>

 <thead>
<row>
<entry><para>Command</para></entry><entry><para>Operation</para></entry>
</row>
</thead>
 <tbody>
<row><entry><para>^D</para></entry><entry><para>Change radix to decimal (base 10)</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para>^O</para></entry><entry><para>Change radix to octal (base 8)</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para>^X</para></entry><entry><para>Change radix to hexidecimal (base 16)</para></entry></row>
 
</tbody>
</tgroup></informaltable>
 </para><para>
 The valid arg2 stand-ins are:
 <informaltable>
 <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="c1"/>
<colspec colname="c2"/>

 <thead>
<row>
<entry><para>Argument</para></entry><entry><para>Value</para></entry>
</row>
</thead>
 <tbody>
<row><entry><para>^.</para></entry><entry><para>Current value of the text buffer pointer</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para>^Z</para></entry><entry><para>Current total number of characters in the text buffer</para></entry></row>
 <row><entry><para>^^x</para></entry><entry><para>The value of character 'x'</para></entry></row>
 
</tbody>
</tgroup></informaltable>
 </para></section></section>
  <section xml:id="APP_VTE_EDT"><title>Editing Text</title>
 <para>
 In addition to allowing you to enter text, the Video Terminal
 Editor macro has a large repertoire of powerful editing commands.
 You request an editing function by using the auxiliary keypad on
 the terminal or by typing control characters or control sequences
 on the standard keyboard. Some functions require you to type
 several keys.
 </para><para>
 When you start the Video Terminal Editor macro with the TECO
 command:
 <informaltable>
 <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="c1"/>
<colspec colname="c2"/>

 <tbody>
<row><entry><para/></entry><entry><para>&ndash;1MI<emphasis role="underline">$$</emphasis></para></entry></row>
 
</tbody>
</tgroup></informaltable>
 </para><para>
 it draws a keypad layout on the screen. This is a summary of the
 available editing functions. You can redisplay this keypad
 layout by using the ESCape H command (see the section on
 Miscellaneous Commands).
 </para><para>
 The following sections describe the editing functions available
 in VTEDIT. When an editing function is equivalent to a simple
 TECO command, the equivalent command appears after the
 description. The macro sounds the terminal bell when it detects
 an error (such as <emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>!, which is an illegal sequence).
 </para>
  <section><title>Moving the Cursor</title>
 <para>
 This section describes the commands which move the cursor around the screen.
 </para>
 <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Set Mark</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Set Mark</refname>
     <refpurpose>Mark the current pointer position.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>9 (keypad key)</command></synopsis>
     <!-- <keypad_section> -->
     <!-- <keypad> -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\closed\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_endrow>(\\) -->
     <!-- <endkeypad> -->
     <!-- <endkeypad_section> --></refsection>
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Mark the current text buffer pointer position for
 use with later commands (see individual commands).
 To move the mark, simply type the 9 key at the new
 position. If you type the 9 key when the pointer
 is at the marked position, the mark is removed and
 the bell sounds. Thus, to remove a mark, type the
 9 key until the bell rings. The mark is always
 removed when it is used.
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Jump</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Jump</refname>
     <refpurpose>Move the pointer to a specific position.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>[n]1 (keypad key)</command></synopsis>
     <!-- <keypad_section> -->
     <!-- <keypad> -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(closed\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_endrow>(\\) -->
     <!-- <endkeypad> -->
     <!-- <endkeypad_section> --></refsection>
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Move the text pointer to position n. If n is not
 given but a mark is set, jump to the mark.
 Otherwise, jump to the beginning of the text
 buffer.
 </para><para>
 In TECO: nJ
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Jump to End of Buffer</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Jump to End of Buffer</refname>
     <refpurpose>Move the pointer to End of Buffer.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>2 (keypad key)</command></synopsis>
     <!-- <keypad_section> -->
     <!-- <keypad> -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\closed\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_endrow>(\\) -->
     <!-- <endkeypad> -->
     <!-- <endkeypad_section> --></refsection>
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Move the text pointer to the end of the text buffer.
 </para><para>
 In TECO: ZJ
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Advance Line</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Advance Line</refname>
     <refpurpose>Move the pointer forward over lines.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>[n]0 (keypad key)</command></synopsis>
     <!-- <keypad_section> -->
     <!-- <keypad> -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_endrow>(closed\\) -->
     <!-- <endkeypad> -->
     <!-- <endkeypad_section> --></refsection>
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Advance the text pointer by n lines, leaving it at
 the beginning of a line.
 </para><para>
 In TECO: nL
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Back Line</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Back Line</refname>
     <refpurpose>Move the pointer backwards over lines.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>[n]4 (keypad key)</command></synopsis>
     <!-- <keypad_section> -->
     <!-- <keypad> -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(closed\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_endrow>(\\) -->
     <!-- <endkeypad> -->
     <!-- <endkeypad_section> --></refsection>
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Back up the text pointer by n lines, leaving it at
 the beginning of a line.
 </para><para>
 In TECO: &ndash;nL
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Start of Line</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Start of Line</refname>
     <refpurpose>Move the pointer to the start of the line.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>3 (keypad key)</command></synopsis>
     <!-- <keypad_section> -->
     <!-- <keypad> -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\closed\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_endrow>(\\) -->
     <!-- <endkeypad> -->
     <!-- <endkeypad_section> --></refsection>
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Move the text pointer to the start of the current line.
 </para><para>
 In TECO: 0L
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>End of Line</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>End of Line</refname>
     <refpurpose>Move the pointer to the end of the line.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>[n]BACKSPACE (special key or CTRL/H)</command></synopsis>
     <!-- <keypad_section> -->
     <!-- <keypad>(display) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(F11\BS\F13\F14) -->
     <!-- <endkeypad> -->
     <!-- <endkeypad_section> --></refsection>
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Move the text pointer to the end of the nth line
 from the current line. If n is not given or is
 equal to 1, move to the end of the current line.
 The end of the line is just before a carriage
 return or form feed.
 </para><para>
 In TECO: nL 2R
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Advance Character</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Advance Character</refname>
     <refpurpose>Move the pointer forward.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>[n]> (right arrow keypad key)</command></synopsis>
     <!-- <keypad_section> -->
     <!-- <keypad> -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\none) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\none) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(none\\none\none) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\closed\none) -->
     <!-- <endkeypad> -->
     <!-- <endkeypad_section> --></refsection>
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Advance the text pointer by n characters.
 </para><para>
 In TECO: nC
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Back Character</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Back Character</refname>
     <refpurpose>Move the pointer backward.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>[n]&larr;(left arrow keypad key)</command></synopsis>
     <!-- <keypad_section> -->
     <!-- <keypad> -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\none) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\none) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(none\\none\none) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(closed\\\none) -->
     <!-- <endkeypad> -->
     <!-- <endkeypad_section> --></refsection>
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Meaning: Back up the text pointer by n characters.
 </para><para>
 In TECO: nR
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Down in Column</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Down in Column</refname>
     <refpurpose>Move the pointer down in the same column.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>[n]&darr;(down arrow keypad key)</command></synopsis>
     <!-- <keypad_section> -->
     <!-- <keypad> -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\none) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\none) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(none\\none\none) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\closed\\none) -->
     <!-- <endkeypad> -->
     <!-- <endkeypad_section> --></refsection>
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Advance the text pointer by n lines, keeping it in
 the same column of the screen if possible. Column
 position is determined by counting characters and
 expanding TABs. If the target line is shorter
 than the position of the pointer at the start, the
 pointer is left at the end of the line. If the
 desired column in the target line is in the middle
 of a tab stop, the pointer is left at the TAB
 character. Repeatedly typing this key and the up
 arrow key preserves the target column, and
 repositions to it when possible.
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Up in Column</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Up in Column</refname>
     <refpurpose>Move the pointer up in the same column.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>[n]&uarr;(up arrow keypad key)</command></synopsis>
     <!-- <keypad_section> -->
     <!-- <keypad> -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\none) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\none) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(none\closed\none\none) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\none) -->
     <!-- <endkeypad> -->
     <!-- <endkeypad_section> --></refsection>
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Back up the text pointer by n lines, keeping it in
 the same column of the screen if possible. Column
 position is determined by counting characters and
 expanding TABs. If the target line is shorter
 than the position of the pointer at the start, the
 pointer is left at the end of the line. If the
 desired column in the target line is in the middle
 of a tab stop, the pointer is left at the TAB
 character. Repeatedly typing this key and the
 down arrow key preserves the target column, and
 repositions to it when possible.
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Advance Word</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Advance Word</refname>
     <refpurpose>Move pointer across words.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>[n]CTRL/F</command></synopsis>
     <para>
      
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>F</keycap>
      
     </para></refsection><refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Advance the text pointer by n words, leaving it at
 the first character of the nth word. Words are
 normally delimited by sequences of spaces, tabs,
 commas, carriage returns, and line feeds. See the
 section on selecting word delimiters.
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Back Word</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Back Word</refname>
     <refpurpose>Move pointer backwards across words.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>[n]CTRL/R</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>R</keycap></para></refsection><refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Back up the text pointer by n words, leaving it at
 the first character of the nth previous word.
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Advance or Back Continuously</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Advance or Back Continuously</refname>
     <refpurpose>Advance or Back Continuously.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command><emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis> followed by one of the six motion commands</command></synopsis></refsection>
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 <emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis> followed by one of the six motion commands for
 advance or back by line (0 or 4 keypad keys),
 character (left or right arrow keypad keys), or
 word (CTRL/F or CTRL/R)
 </para><para>
 Move the text pointer continuously by one unit
 (line, character, or word) in the selected
 direction, updating the screen each time the
 pointer moves. You can stop the motion by typing
 any non-keypad key. The character typed to stop
 the motion is otherwise ignored. Motion also
 stops (and the bell sounds) when the text pointer
 reaches the beginning or end of the buffer.
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Advance Screen Image</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Advance Screen Image</refname>
     <refpurpose>Move the pointer forward one full screen image.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>&darr;(ESCape, down arrow keypad key)</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>&darr;</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Advance the text pointer the correct number of lines to move the current bottom line of
      the screen to just off the top of the screen. This allows you to 'page' through the text
      buffer. Overflow lines (lines too long for the screen) and overprint lines will cause slightly
      more or less than one screen's worth of data to be passed over. </para>
     <para> In TECO: 24L </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Back Screen Image</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Back Screen Image</refname>
     <refpurpose>Move the pointer backwards one full screen image.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>&uarr;(ESCape, up arrow keypad key)</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>&uarr;</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Back up the text pointer the correct number of lines to move the current top line of the
      screen to just off the bottom of the screen. This allows you to 'page' through the text
      buffer. Overflow lines (lines too long for the screen) and overprint lines will cause slightly
      more or less than one screen's worth of data to be passed over. </para>
     <para> In TECO: &ndash;24L </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Back Over Last Operation</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Back Over Last Operation</refname>
     <refpurpose>Back up the pointer to where it was before the last operation.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command><emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>6 (ESCape, 6 keypad key)</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>6</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Back up the text pointer the correct number of characters position it to where it was
      prior to the last operation. For example, if you have just saved some text with the PF1 keypad
      key, then this would re-position you to the start of the saved text. </para>
     <para> In TECO: ^SC </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
 </section>
 <section><title>Searching Text</title>
 <para>
 This section describes the commands which search for the occurrence of
 specific text strings.
 </para>
 <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Set Search Argument and Search Text Buffer</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Set Search Argument and Search Text Buffer</refname>
     <refpurpose>Search the current text buffer for string.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>[n]ENTER (keypad key)</command></synopsis></refsection>
 <!-- <keypad_section> -->
 <!-- <keypad> -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_endrow>(\\closed) -->
 <!-- <endkeypad> -->
 <!-- <endkeypad_section> -->
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Get a search argument from the keyboard and search
 for the nth occurence of it in the text buffer.
 When you type the ENTER key, VTEDIT erases the top
 two lines of the screen and prompts you for a
 search argument with 'Buffer search:'. Your
 previous search argument (from any kind of search)
 is initially displayed following the prompt. If
 you wish to reuse your previous argument, simply
 type either the keypad period (.) or a double
 ESCape. To edit your previous argument, type an
 initial RUBOUT. This deletes the last character
 of your argument, but retains the rest as if you
 had just entered it. Further editing and/or entry
 is now done in the normal way. Any other initial
 keystroke erases the entire previous search
 argument; you may now proceed to enter your new
 argument. The search argument may be any valid
 TECO search construct. Your search string appears
 on the screen as you type. You can use RUBOUT to
 edit your typing, and you can type CTRL/U to
 abandon the entry of the search string, abort the
 search command, and clean up the screen. When you
 are ready to perform the search, type either the
 keypad period (.) or a double ESCape. VTEDIT
 cleans up the screen, saves the search argument,
 and positions the pointer after the nth occurence
 of the string within the text buffer. If n is
 negative, the search is done backwards in the
 buffer. If the string is found and there is no
 active mark set, the found string is shown in
 reverse video (on those terminals that support it)
 until the next keystroke. If the string is not
 found, VTEDIT moves the pointer to the start of
 the text buffer and sounds the bell.
 </para><para>
 In TECO: n:Stext<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Set Search Argument and Search through File</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Set Search Argument and Search through File</refname>
     <refpurpose>Search the rest of the file for string.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]CTRL/N</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>N</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> This command is similar to the previous one, but performs a through the whole file
      search. If you do not have an open output file, the terminal bell rings and the command is
      ignored. The prompt is 'File search:'. During the file searching, the cursor is positioned in
      the upper left corner of the screen. If the nth occurance is not found, the bell sounds (the
      text buffer will be empty). </para>
     <para> In TECO: n:Ntext<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>
     </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Set Search Argument and Destructively Search File</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Set Search Argument and Destructively Search File</refname>
     <refpurpose>Search the rest of the file for a string without output.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>CTRL/N</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>N</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> This command is similiar to the previous one, but doesn't output passed over text. If
      you have an open output file and destructive mode (bit 1, value 2) in the TECO edit mode flag
      (ED) is not set, the terminal bell rings and the command is ignored. The prompt is
      'Destructive file search:'. During the file searching, the cursor is positioned in the upper
      left corner of the screen. If the nth occurance is not found, the bell sounds (the text buffer
      will be empty). </para>
     <para> In TECO: n:_text<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>
     </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Search Again</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
<refname>Search Again</refname>
<refpurpose>
 Perform the same search as before.
 </refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>[n]. (keypad key)</command></synopsis></refsection>
 <!-- <keypad_section> -->
 <!-- <keypad> -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_endrow>(\closed\) -->
 <!-- <endkeypad> -->
 <!-- <endkeypad_section> -->
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Search in the text buffer for the nth occurence of
 the search argument which was most recently saved
 via any search command. If n is negative, the
 search is done backwards in the buffer. If you
 have not yet used the ENTER command, VTEDIT
 searches for the string you most recently searched
 for from TECO before you started VTEDIT. If the
 string is not found, VTEDIT moves the pointer to
 the start of the text buffer and sounds the bell.
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
 </section>
 <section><title>Deleting Text</title>
 <para>
 This section describes the commands for deleting text.
 </para>
 <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Rub Out Character</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Rub Out Character</refname>
     <refpurpose>Delete the character before the pointer.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]DEL</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap><!-- <delete_key> --></keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Delete n characters before the text pointer, starting with the character before the
      cursor. </para>
     <para> In TECO: &ndash;nD </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Delete Character</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Delete Character</refname>
     <refpurpose>Delete the character after the pointer.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>[n]5 (keypad key)</command></synopsis></refsection>
 <!-- <keypad_section> -->
 <!-- <keypad> -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\closed\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_endrow>(\\) -->
 <!-- <endkeypad> -->
 <!-- <endkeypad_section> -->
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Delete n characters, starting with the character
 under the cursor.
 </para><para>
 In TECO: nD
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Rub Out Word</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Rub Out Word</refname>
     <refpurpose>Delete the word before the pointer.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]CTRL/B</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>B</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Delete the text between the start of the nth previous word and the current text pointer.
     </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Delete Word</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Delete Word</refname>
     <refpurpose>Delete the word after the pointer.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>CTRL/B</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>B</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Delete the text between the current text pointer and the start of the n+1st word beyond
      the pointer. </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Rub Out Line</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Rub Out Line</refname>
     <refpurpose>Delete from start-of-line to pointer.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>CTRL/U</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>U</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Delete the text between the start of the current line and the text pointer. </para>
     <para> In TECO: 0K </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Delete Line</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Delete Line</refname>
     <refpurpose>Delete the rest of the line.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]CTRL/K</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>K</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Delete n lines of text, starting at the current text pointer (the character under the
      cursor). If n is not given but a mark is set, delete the text between the mark and the current
      text pointer. Otherwise, delete one line. </para>
     <para> In TECO: nK </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Delete Rest of Line</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Delete Rest of Line</refname>
     <refpurpose>Delete from the pointer to end-of-line.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]CTRL/D</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>D</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Delete the text between the current text pointer and the end of the nth line from the
      pointer. The carriage return and line feed at the end of the nth line (if any) are not
      deleted. </para>
     <para> In TECO: nK 13I<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis> 10I<emphasis role="underline"
       >$</emphasis> 2R </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Delete or Restore Text</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Delete or Restore Text</refname>
     <refpurpose>Delete selected text or restore what was just deleted.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>6 (keypad key)</command></synopsis></refsection>
 <!-- <keypad_section> -->
 <!-- <keypad> -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\closed\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_endrow>(\\) -->
 <!-- <endkeypad> -->
 <!-- <endkeypad_section> -->
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 If the previous keystroke was a VTEDIT deletion
 command, restore the deleted text and return the
 buffer pointer to its former position. Otherwise,
 delete the spanned text block. The spanned text
 is the text most recently located or inserted in
 the text buffer via a Cut, Paste, Search, Get, or
 Exchange command, or by a restoring 6.
 </para><para>
 In TECO: .+^S,.K
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
 </section>
 <section><title>Inserting and Moving Text</title>
 <para>
 This section describes the commands that insert and move text.
 </para>
 <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Open Line</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Open Line</refname>
     <refpurpose>Insert an empty line into the text buffer.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>[n]7 (keypad key)</command></synopsis></refsection>
 <!-- <keypad_section> -->
 <!-- <keypad> -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(closed\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_endrow>(\\) -->
 <!-- <endkeypad> -->
 <!-- <endkeypad_section> -->
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Insert n return/line feed sequences after the
 current text pointer. The effect of this command
 is to move the rest of the text on the current
 line down to a new line.
 </para><para>
 In TECO: n&lt;13I<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis> 10I<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>> 2*nR
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Get Q-register Contents</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Get Q-register Contents</refname>
     <refpurpose>Load q-register into text buffer.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>CTRL/Gq</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>G</keycap>+<keycap>q</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Insert the contents of Q-register q in the text buffer. In this command, q can be any
      alphabetic or numeric Q-register name, or it can be either of the special names '*' (file name
      buffer) and '_' (search string buffer). </para>
     <para> In TECO: Gq </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Load Q-register</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Load Q-register</refname>
     <refpurpose>Load q-register from text buffer.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]CTRL/X[:]q</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>X</keycap>+<keycap>q</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Copy n lines from the text buffer into Q-register q. If n is not given and there is a
      mark set, copy the text between the mark and the current text pointer. Otherwise, copy one
      line. VTEDIT moves the text pointer to the end of the copied text. If the colon is present,
      append the text to the Q-register instead of copying it. You can not specify Q-register I. <note>
       <para> If you are using VAX/VMS, CTRL/X is intercepted by the terminal service as cancel all
        type ahead. You can use a combination of CTRL/T and CTRL/G to cut and restore text to
        Q-registers. </para>
      </note>
     </para>
     <para> In TECO: nXq </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Load Q-register and Delete Text</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Load Q-register and Delete Text</refname>
     <refpurpose>Load q-register from text buffer and delete.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]CTRL/T[:]q</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>T</keycap>+<keycap>q</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Similar to CTRL/X, but delete the copied text. </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Save Text</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Save Text</refname>
     <refpurpose>Save text into the cut buffer.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>[n]PF1 (keypad key)</command></synopsis></refsection>
 <!-- <keypad_section> -->
 <!-- <keypad> -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(closed\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_endrow>(\\) -->
 <!-- <endkeypad> -->
 <!-- <endkeypad_section> -->
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Copy n lines from the text buffer into the VTEDIT
 cut buffer. If n is not given and there is a mark
 set, copy the text between the mark and the
 current text pointer. Otherwise, copy one line.
 VTEDIT moves the text pointer to the end of the
 copied text. If you repeatedly type the PF1 key
 with no intervening keystrokes, VTEDIT appends
 successive lines of text to the cut buffer. You
 can delete the text which was cut by typing the 6
 keypad key.
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Paste Text</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Paste Text</refname>
     <refpurpose>Insert cut buffer into text.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>PF3 (keypad key)</command></synopsis></refsection>
 <!-- <keypad_section> -->
 <!-- <keypad> -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\closed\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_endrow>(\\) -->
 <!-- <endkeypad> -->
 <!-- <endkeypad_section> -->
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Insert the contents of the cut buffer into the text buffer.
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Insert ASCII Value</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Insert ASCII Value</refname>
     <refpurpose>Insert literal character in text buffer.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]CTRL/\</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>\</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Accept a character from the terminal and insert into the text buffer the string
      representing the ASCII value of that character. If n is present, insert the string
      representing n and do not accept an extra character. VTEDIT inserts the number using the radix
      that was set when you started the macro. You can change this radix by executing a TECO command
      with the PF2 key or CTRL/E function. </para>
     <para> In TECO: ^^x\ (where x is the next character you type) </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Insert Special Character</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Insert Special Character</refname>
     <refpurpose>Insert character into the text buffer.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>n9 (keypad key)</command></synopsis></refsection>
 <!-- <keypad_section> -->
 <!-- <keypad> -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\closed\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_endrow>(\\) -->
 <!-- <endkeypad> -->
 <!-- <endkeypad_section> -->
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Insert into the text buffer the character whose ASCII value is n.
 </para><para>
 In TECO: nI<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
 </section>
 <section><title>Advancing through the Input File</title>
 <para>
 This section describes the commands that are used to read the input file.
 </para>
 <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Advance Page</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Advance Page</refname>
     <refpurpose>Move pointer across pages of text.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>[n]8 (keypad key)</command></synopsis></refsection>
 <!-- <keypad_section> -->
 <!-- <keypad> -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\closed\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
 <!-- <keypad_endrow>(\\) -->
 <!-- <endkeypad> -->
 <!-- <endkeypad_section> -->
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Go forward n pages in the file(s) being edited.
 If you do not have an open output file, the
 terminal bell sounds and the command is ignored.
 </para><para>
 In TECO: nP
 </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Append Page or Line</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Append Page or Line</refname>
     <refpurpose>Append a page or a line of text to the buffer.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]CTRL/A</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>A</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Append the next n pages from the input file to the current text buffer. If n is 0,
      append only one line from the file. If n is negative (e.g., <emphasis role="underline"
       >$</emphasis>&ndash;CTRL/A), keep appending pages from the input file until end-of-file. If
      there are form feeds separating the text in the file, VTEDIT inserts form feeds in the text
      buffer. </para>
     <para> In TECO: n&lt; ^E"T 12I<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis> ' A > </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Append Page or Line with no Form Feeds</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Append Page or Line with no Form Feeds</refname>
     <refpurpose>Append a page or a line of text and discard form feeds.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>CTRL/A</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>A</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Append the next n pages from the input file to the current text buffer, discarding any
      form feeds that appear in the input file. If n is negative (e.g., <emphasis role="underline"
       >$</emphasis>&ndash;<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>CTRL/A), keep appending pages from
      the input file until end-of-file. If n is 0, append only one line from the file. </para>
     <para> In TECO: n&lt; A > </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Yank Page</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Yank Page</refname>
     <refpurpose>Get a new page from the input file.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>Y</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>Y</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Yank n pages, leaving the nth page in the text buffer. If you have an open output file
      and destructive mode (bit 1, value 2) in TECO's edit mode flag (ED) is not set, the terminal
      bell rings and the command is ignored. </para>
     <para> In TECO: n&lt; Y > </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Inhibit Yank Protection</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Inhibit Yank Protection</refname>
     <refpurpose/>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command><emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>&ndash;<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>Y</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>&ndash;</keycap>+<keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>Y</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> This command inhibits yank protection; it sets destructive mode (bit 1, value 2) in
      TECO's edit mode flag (ED). </para>
     <para> In TECO: 0,2ED </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Enable Yank Protection</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Enable Yank Protection</refname>
     <refpurpose/>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command><emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>0<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>Y</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>0</keycap>+<keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>Y</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> This command enables yank protection; it clears destructive mode (bit 1, value 2) in
      TECO's edit mode flag (ED). </para>
     <para> In TECO: 2,0ED </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
 </section>
 <section><title>Executing TECO commands</title>
 <para>
 This section describes the commands that enable you to execute TECO commands
 under control of the VTEDIT macro.
 </para>
 <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Execute Q-register Macro</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Execute Q-register Macro</refname>
     <refpurpose>Execute a macro contained in a q-register.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]CTRL/Eq</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>E</keycap>+<keycap>q</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Execute the macro in Q-register q. If n is present, use its value as an argument to the
      macro; if not, execute the macro with no argument. VTEDIT moves the cursor to the top left
      corner of the screen while the macro is being executed. </para>
     <para> In TECO: nMq or Mq </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Repeat Q-register Macro</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Repeat Q-register Macro</refname>
     <refpurpose>Repeatedly execute a macro in a q-register.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>CTRL/Eq</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>E</keycap>+<keycap>q</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Execute the macro in Q-register q in an iteration loop. If the value of n is zero, the
      iteration is infinite. Otherwise, n is the iteration count for the loop. If n is not given,
      this command is the same as CTRL/Eq. </para>
     <para> In TECO: n&lt; Mq > or &lt; Mq > </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Set TECO Command and Execute</refentrytitle>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
     <refname>Set TECO Command and Execute</refname>
     <refpurpose>Load a TECO command and execute it.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

 
 <refsection><title>Syntax</title><synopsis><command>[n]PF2 (keypad key)</command></synopsis>
     <!-- <keypad_section> -->
     <!-- <keypad> -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\closed\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_row>(\\\) -->
     <!-- <keypad_endrow>(\\) -->
     <!-- <endkeypad> -->
     <!-- <endkeypad_section> --></refsection>
 <refsection><title>Description</title><para>
 Get a TECO command from the keyboard and execute
 it. When you type the PF2 keypad key, VTEDIT
 erases the top two lines of the screen and prompts
 you for a command. Your previous command string
 is initially displayed following the 'Command:'
 prompt. If you wish to reuse your previous
 command, simply type either the keypad period (.)
 or a double ESCape. To edit your previous
 command, type an initial RUBOUT. This deletes the
 last character of your command, but retains the
 rest as if you had just entered it. Further
 editing and/or entry is now done in the normal
 way. Any other initial keystroke erases the
 entire previous command string; you may now
 proceed to enter your new command. You may enter
 any valid TECO command string. Your command
 string appears on the screen as you type. You can
 use RUBOUT to edit your typing, and you can type
 CTRL/U to abandon the entry of the command, bypass
 command execution, and clean up the screen. When
 you are ready to execute the command, type the
 keypad period (.) or a double ESCape. VTEDIT
 cleans up the screen, saves the command string,
 and executes the command. VTEDIT moves the cursor
 to the top left corner of the screen while the
 command is being executed.
 </para><para>
 If n is present, its value is used as an argument
 to the TECO command string.
 </para><para> In TECO:<simplelist>
       <member>^U9command<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis> nM9 </member>
       <member>^U9command<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis> M9 </member>
      </simplelist><note>
       <para> VTEDIT truely stores the TECO command in Q-register 9. A subsequent CTRL/G 9 command
        will insert the command into the text buffer. To save the command in an alphabetic
        Q-register for later usage, You can use the following keystroke sequence: <informaltable>
         <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec colname="c1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2"/>
          <tbody>
           <row>
            <entry>
             <para>9</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
             <para>Keypad key 9 to set a mark</para>
            </entry>
           </row>
           <row>
            <entry>
             <para>CTRL/G 9</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
             <para>Get TECO command from Q-register 9</para>
            </entry>
           </row>
           <row>
            <entry>
             <para>CTRL/T q</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
             <para>Take command away to Q-register q</para>
            </entry>
           </row>
          </tbody>
         </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
       </para>
      </note>
     </para></refsection>
 </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Re-execute TECO Command</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Re-execute TECO Command</refname>
     <refpurpose>Execute stored TECO command.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]<emphasis role="underline">$$</emphasis></command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>Esc</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Execute the TECO command most recently set with the PF2 keypad key. VTEDIT moves the
      cursor to the top left corner of the screen while the command is being executed. </para>
     <para> If n is present, its value is used as an argument to the TECO command. </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Set TECO Command and Repeat Execution</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Set TECO Command and Repeat Execution</refname>
     <refpurpose>Get a TECO command and repeatedly execute it.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>PF2 (keypad key)</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>PF2</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> A TECO command is gotten from the keyboard just like the PF2 command. If n is present,
      the TECO command is executed n times. Else the TECO command is executed in an infinite
      iteration. </para>
     <para> In TECO: <informaltable>
       <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
        <colspec colname="c1"/>
        <colspec colname="c2"/>
        <tbody>
         <row>
          <entry>
           <para/>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>^U9command<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis> n&lt; M9 ></para>
          </entry>
         </row>
         <row>
          <entry>
           <para/>
          </entry>
          <entry>
           <para>^U9command<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis> &lt; M9 ></para>
          </entry>
         </row>
        </tbody>
       </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
     </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Start/End Learning Mode</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Start/End Learning Mode</refname>
     <refpurpose>Enter a command sequence and remember it.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command><emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>L</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>L</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> VTEDIT can 'learn' a series of keystrokes and (re-)execute them upon request. An initial
       <emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>L puts VTEDIT into learning mode. Every subsequent
      keystroke is remembered by VTEDIT until another <emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>L is
      typed. To cancel a learned sequence or to ensure that you are out of learning mode, type
       <emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>L until the terminal bell sounds. The bell signals
      that the null learning sequence (i.e., <emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>L<emphasis
       role="underline">$</emphasis>L) has been entered. </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Execute Learned Sequence</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Execute Learned Sequence</refname>
     <refpurpose>Execute a previously remembered command sequence.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>X</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>X</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> This command causes VTEDIT to (re-)execute the previously learned keystroke sequence. If
      you do not have any learning sequence remembered, the terminal bell rings. The optional
      numeric argument is the number of times to execute the learned keystroke sequence. </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
 </section>
 <section><title>Controlling the Video Terminal</title>
 <para>
 This section describes the commands that are used to control the display.
 </para>
 <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Repaint Screen</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Repaint Screen</refname>
     <refpurpose>Repaint.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>CTRL/W</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>W</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Repaint the screen. This command is useful if the display on the screen is destroyed by
      a broadcast from the system manager. This command also restores special keypad mode on the
      editing keypad, and can be used if the terminal was powered down. </para>
     <para> VTEDIT requests your terminal to send its terminal id as part of this command. You
      should, therefore, wait until the screen stops updating/flickering before further typing. As
      part of the screen repaint, a series of ESCape sequences are sent to the terminal. </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Set Cursor Line</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Set Cursor Line</refname>
     <refpurpose>Set the position of the line where the cursor remains.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>nCTRL/W</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>n</keycap>+<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>W</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> The cursor line is set to n. The scope driver will try to keep the cursor on the nth
      line of the screen. The initial value of this cursor line is 2/3rd's of the way down the
      screen (16 for 24 line screens). </para>
     <para> An effective CTRL/W command is executed after setting the cursor line; please read the
      notes above. </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Toggle See-all Display Mode</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Toggle See-all Display Mode</refname>
     <refpurpose>Set screen mode so that all characters are displayed.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>CTRL/V</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>V</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> This command turns on the scope driver see-all mode, or turns it off if it is currently
      on. </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Set Terminal Characteristics</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Set Terminal Characteristics</refname>
     <refpurpose>Set the characteristics of the terminal.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>nCTRL/V</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>n</keycap>+<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>V</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Change the display characteristics of the terminal. VTEDIT requests your terminal to
      send its terminal id as part of this command. You should, therefore, wait until the screen
      stops updating/flickering before further typing. If you have selected some illegal terminal
      characteristic, VTEDIT should catch it and automatically establish something that will work. </para>
     <para> If n has the value 0, VTEDIT tells the scope driver that your terminal is a VT52. Use
      this command only if TECO made a wrong guess when it started (which shouldn't happen) or if
      you detach and change terminal types during an editing session. The value 2 means that the
      terminal is a DEC_CRT, but should be controlled in VT52 compatibility mode. The value 4 means
      that the terminal is a DEC_CRT and should be controlled with ANSI standard escape sequences.
      This is the optimal setting for DEC_CRT terminals, and must be used if you want to display 132
      columns or to display the marked region in reverse video. When you change modes on a DEC_CRT,
      the VTEDIT sends the proper escape sequence to the terminal to change its operation. </para>
     <para> If n has an even value from 10 to 132, that value is used as the new width for the
      display. You must be in DEC_CRT ANSI mode to set a width greater than 80. You can set a width
      narrower than terminal can display. Setting a width wider than your terminal can handle may
      cause unpredicatble results. Note that the scope driver reserves the last two characters of
      each line, and therefore can display only n&ndash;2 characters if the width is set to n. The
      default width is 80 characters when you start VTEDIT. </para>
     <para> If n has a negative value from 10 to 24, it sets the height of the display. You should
      not use this command, unless you have a DEC_CRT in ANSI mode which has the capability to
      change the hardware scrolling region. </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Enter/Exit Screen Holding Mode</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Enter/Exit Screen Holding Mode</refname>
     <refpurpose>Toggle hold screen mode. </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>CTRL/V</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>V</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> This command toggles "holding screen" mode. In normal mode (the default), VTEDIT
      attempts to keep the cursor positioned on the line specified by the nCTRL/W command. Any
      advance or back line command will scroll the screen one line thus keeping the cursor in the
      same physical location on the screen. In holding screen mode, VTEDIT will only scroll the
      screen when the cursor position would have been off the screen. For example, an advance line
      from the last line on the screen or a back line from the top line on the screen will cause the
      screen to scroll and the cursor to be positioned at its default location, the line specified
      by nCTRL/W. This mode is useful for terminals without reverse scrolling capabilities and/or
      for operation over a low speed communication lines. </para>
     <para> If n is present and has the value 0, holding screen mode is unconditionally turned off;
      if n is -1, holding screen mode is unconditionally turned on. </para>
     <para> If n is positive, holding screen mode is turned on with the cursor limit set to n.
      VTEDIT will only scroll the screen if the cursor position would have been within the top or
      bottom n lines on the screen. <note>
       <para> This feature only works on VT52 terminals and should not be used on DEC_CRT terminals.
       </para>
      </note>
     </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
 </section>
 
 <section><title>Selecting Word Delimiters</title>
 <para>
 Several of the VTEDIT editing commands use the idea of a 'word'
 in the text buffer. Normally, words are delimited by sequences
 of spaces, tabs, commas, carriage returns, and line feeds. If
 you have a special editing application, you may require a
 different definition of a word. The following commands allow you
 to change that definition.
 </para>
 <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Use Standard Words</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Use Standard Words</refname>
     <refpurpose> Set the standard word delimiting characters. </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command><emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>T</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>T</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Restore the set of word delimiters to the standard set: space, tab, comma, carriage
      return, line feed. </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Use BASIC-PLUS Words</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Use BASIC-PLUS Words</refname>
     <refpurpose> Use the BASIC-PLUS word delimiting characters. </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command><emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>0<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>T</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>0</keycap>+<keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>T</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Use a set of word delimiters appropriate for editing BASIC-PLUS code. This command
      appends the following special characters to the set of word delimiters: </para>
     <para> &lpar; &rpar; + -&star; ^ \ ! = : &lt; > / </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Clear Delimiter Set</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Clear Delimiter Set</refname>
     <refpurpose> Clear word delimiting characters. </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command><emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>&ndash;<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>T</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>&ndash;</keycap>+<keycap>ESC</keycap>+<keycap>T</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Clear out the word delimiter set. You must follow this command by adding one or more
      word delimiters (see below). </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Add Word Delimiter</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Add Word Delimiter</refname>
     <refpurpose> Add characters to the word delimiters. </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>n<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>T</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>n</keycap>+<keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>T</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Add the character whose ASCII value is n to the set of word delimiters. The value of n
      must be between 1 and 127. </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Get Next Word</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Get Next Word</refname>
     <refpurpose> Move word(s) from surrounding lines to current line. </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>N</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>N</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Move the next n words to the current line. If n is positive, the cursor should be at the
      end of a line; the first n words of the next line(s) are moved to the end of the current line.
      If n is negative, the cursor should be at the beginning of a line; the last n words of the
      previous line(s) are moved to the beginning of the current line. </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
 </section>
 <section><title>Exiting</title>
 <para>
 This section describes the commands used to exit from VTEDIT and TECO.
 </para>
 <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Exit from VTEDIT</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Exit from VTEDIT</refname>
     <refpurpose> </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>CTRL/Z or CTRL/C</command></synopsis>
     <para>
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>Z</keycap> or
       <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>C</keycap>
      </para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Exit from the Video Terminal Editor macro to TECO's asterisk prompt. </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Exit from TECO</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Exit from TECO</refname>
     <refpurpose> Exit from TECO. </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command><emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>CTRL/Z</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>Z</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Exit from the Video Terminal Editor macro and from TECO, copying the input file to the
      output file and closing both files. This command turns off special keypad mode and moves the
      cursor to the bottom of the screen. </para>
     <para> In TECO: EX </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Exit from TECO Without Preserving Output</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Exit from TECO Without Preserving Output</refname>
     <refpurpose> Exit from TECO and undo all changes. </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command><emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>&ndash;CTRL/Z</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>&ndash;</keycap>+<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>Z</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Delete any output file which may be open, undo any edit backup in effect, and exit from
      TECO. This command turns off special keypad mode and moves the cursor to the bottom of the
      screen. </para>
     <para> In TECO: HK EK EX </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
 </section>
 <section><title>Miscellaneous Commands</title>
 <para>
 This section describes the rest of the commands.
 </para>
 <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Find Front of File</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Find Front of File</refname>
     <refpurpose> Go back to the beginning of the file. </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command><emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>F</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>F</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> The current file open for editing is closed out and, then, re-opened. You are left
      positioned at the first page of the file. If you have no current output file the terminal bell
      sounds and the command is ignored. </para>
     <para> In TECO: EC EBfile<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis> Y </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Worry About Operating System Crashing</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Worry About Operating System Crashing</refname>
     <refpurpose> Close the edit session and re-open at the current point. </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command><emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>1<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>F</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>1</keycap>+<keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>F</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Close out the file currently open for editing, re-open it, and re-find your current
      editing position. Similiar to the command above, but automatically re-positions you to where
      you left off editing. This command is useful if your operating system tends to crash...
     </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Exit from TECO Marking Position</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Exit from TECO Marking Position</refname>
     <refpurpose> Exit TECO but remember where you are. </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command><emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>0<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>F</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>0</keycap>+<keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>F</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Close out the file currently open for editing marking the current editing position.
      TECO's memory file is updated to reflect the file currently being edited and the /FIND switch
      is appended to the file specification. This command is used in conjunction with the command
      below. </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Find Marked Position</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Find Marked Position</refname>
     <refpurpose> Find the point where you stopped editing. </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command><emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>&ndash;<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>F</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>&ndash;</keycap>+<keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>F</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> (Re-)find marked editing position. The editing position marked by some previous
       <emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>0<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>F command is
      re-found. </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Redisplay Keypad Layout</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Redisplay Keypad Layout</refname>
     <refpurpose> Help for keypad. </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command><emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>H</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>H</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Clear the screen and display the help text for the Video Terminal Editing macro. Type
      any non-keypad character to redisplay the text window and resume editing. VTEDIT does not
      insert that character into the text. </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
  <refentry>
    <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>Set Left Margin</refentrytitle>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
     <refname>Set Left Margin</refname>
     <refpurpose> Set the position of the left margin. </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
     <title>Syntax</title>
     <synopsis><command>[n]<emphasis role="underline">$</emphasis>M</command></synopsis>
     <para><keycap>Esc</keycap>+<keycap>M</keycap></para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
     <title>Description</title>
     <para> Set the left margin at column n. If you have set a left margin, the VTEDIT automatically
      inserts enough tabs and spaces to get the cursor to the margin whenever you type a carriage
      return or an open line command (7 key on keypad). If n is negative, VTEDIT sets the margin to
      &ndash;n and uses only spaces for filling. If n is not present, the margin is set at the
      current column. If there is any text on the line when this you give this command, VTEDIT
      shifts it to the new margin. </para>
    </refsection>
   </refentry>
 </section>
  </section>
 </appendix>
