<?xml version="1.0"?>
<chapter xml:id="bas" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <title>Basics of TECO</title>
  <section xml:id="bas_using">
    <title>Using TECO</title>
    <para>
      TECO may be called from command level by typing the appropriate
      command, followed by a carriage return:
    </para>
    <table>
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>Operating System</entry><entry>Command</entry>
        </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>RT-11</entry><entry>R TECO</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>OS/8</entry><entry>R TECO</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>TOPS-10</entry><entry>R TECO</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>TOPS-20</entry><entry>R TECO</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>RSTS/E</entry><entry>RUN TECO$:TECO --or--</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry></entry><entry>EDIT/TECO</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>RSX-11</entry><entry>RUN $TEC</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>VAX/VMS</entry><entry>RUN SYS$SYSTEM:TECO32</entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </table>
    <para>
      TECO will respond by printing an asterisk at the left margin to
      indicate that it is ready to accept user commands. At this
      point, you may type one or more commands.
      <indexterm><primary>Command</primary></indexterm>
    </para>
    <para>
      A <firstterm>TECO command</firstterm> consists of one or two
      characters which cause a specific operation to be performed.
      Some TECO commands may be
      <indexterm><primary>Command arguments</primary></indexterm>
      preceded or followed by <firstterm>arguments</firstterm>. Arguments
      may be either
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Command arguments</primary>
        <secondary>numeric</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Command arguments</primary>
        <secondary>textual</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <firstterm>numeric</firstterm> or <firstterm>textual</firstterm>. A
      numeric argument is simply an integer value which can be used to
      indicate, for example, the number of times a command should be
      executed. A text argument is a string of ASCII characters which might
      be, for example, words of text or a file specification.
    </para>
    <para>
      If a command requires a numeric argument, the numeric argument
      always precedes the command. If a command requires a text
      argument, the text argument always follows the command. Each
      text argument is terminated by a special character (usually a
      (&lt;DELIM&gt;) character, which TECO hears as an ESCape - see
      Introduction). This indicates to TECO that the next character
      typed will be the first character of a new command.
    </para>
    <para>
      TECO accumulates commands as they are typed in a
      <firstterm>command string</firstterm>, and executes commands upon
      receipt of two consecutive &lt;DELIM&gt; characters. &lt;DELIM&gt;
      may be any character you select (if your TECO and operating system
      support user-selectable ESCape surrogates - see sections on ET and
      EE flags). When you type the character you have designated as
      &lt;DELIM&lt;, TECO receives an ESCape character, and an
      ` (accent grave) is echoed.
      (If you are not using an ESCape surrogate -- that is, you are
      actually pressing an ESCape key -- a dollar sign is echoed.) The
      <firstterm>accent grave</firstterm> character is used in examples
      throughout this manual to represent typed &lt;DELIM&gt;s. Note that
      the carriage return character has no special significance to TECO;
      only the &lt;DELIM&gt;&lt;DELIM&gt; forces execution of the command
      string.
    </para>
    <para>
      TECO executes command strings from left to right until either all
      commands have been executed or a
      <firstterm>command error</firstterm> is recognized. It then prints
      an asterisk to signal that additional commands may be entered.
    </para>
    <para>
      If TECO encounters an erroneous command, it prints an error
      message and ignores the erroneous command as well as all commands
      which follow it. All error messages are of the form:
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
